Ruth Pierson Churchill Papers, 1919-1988
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Ruth Pierson Churchill papers
1919-1988
1919-1929
Churchill, Ruth Pierson, 1896-
MS 402
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Smith graduate and WWI relief worker. The bulk of the papers documents her relief work for the Foreign Missions Board of the Methodist Church in France, during World War I. Papers include photographs, a scrapbook, postcards, news clippings, and an outline of Church's service in France. Also included is correspondence between Churchill and her family, friends, and U.S. servicemen.
Ruth Vail Pierson Churchill, born August 22, 1896, graduated from Smith College with the Class of 1919. Following graduation, Churchill (then Pierson) went to the city of Chateau-Thierry, France, to work for the Foreign Missions Board of the Methodist Church. She went in response to a letter of request from Rev. Albert Hall Marion and his wife Eva, dated July 15, 1919. Marion was a family friend and minister from Churchill's hometown of Madison, New Jersey. He had served in the YMCA during the war, returned to France following the armistice, and was appointed the Director of the Chateau-Thierry Methodist Memorial under the auspices of the Eglise Methodiste Episcopale de France's War Relief Committee. Churchill was assigned to assist in construction, supply, medical, and morale projects in Chateau-Thierry, including the village of Crezancy. Although the work was similar to the undertakings of the Smith College Relief Unit (working nearby on the Somme River), the group Churchill worked with was under the control of the Methodist Church, and not directly connected to Smith College or its war relief efforts.
Churchill left France in May 1920. In the years following she maintained contact with many of the friends she met there, and continued her commitment to public service. She remained active in Smith College alumnae activities: she served in various capacities for her class beginning in 1939 through the 1980s; she was corresponding secretary and then president of the Summit Smith Club from 1938-1943; and she was president of the Alumnae Association from 1947-1950. She also worked on the 25th reunion book for her class in 1944, and the college's 75th Anniversary Fund from 1946-1947. Church was also an active participant in community affairs in Morris County, New Jersey. She worked with the Defense Council of Madison, the War Price and Rationing Board, the Women's Republican Club, the League of Women Voters, the Red Cross, the Morris County Welfare Board, the Madison Public Library, the Madison and Chatham Township Historical Societies, the Community Church of Summit, and the Daughters of the American Revolution. She also wrote occasional columns for the Chatham Courier and the Madison Eagle.
Ruth Pierson Churchill died August 16, 1999, one week before her 103rd birthday. She left three children: Martha Churchill Drake (class of 1950), Emily Churchill Wood (class of 1946) and John Churchill.
The World War I Relief Work Papers of Ruth V. Pierson Churchill consist of 5 linear inches of correspondence, photographs and other material dating from 1918-1988. The bulk of the material dates from 1919-1929 and relates to the two years she spent in France from 1919-1920. There is correspondence from Churchill to her family during her work in France (1919-1920), as well as letters to Churchill from friends she met there (1919-1971). The friends include Jeannine Issartel, Simone Plateau, Veuve Harle, Leone Provost Fauve, and others. There are several letters from U.S. servicemen serving overseas in 1918 (including her brother-in-law), the original letter from Rev. Albert Hall Marion requesting Church's services (July 15, 1919), as well as a bank book and a scrapbook kept by Church while in France. There are also a variety of photographs, postcards and news clippings, and an outline of Church's service in France, written by Church herself in 1965.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biography
II. Correspondence
III. Photographs and Memorabilia
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The papers of Ruth V. Pierson Churchill relating to her relief work in France following World War I (1919-1920) were given to the Smith College Archives as part of a larger donation which included papers concerning her time as a student at the school (1916-1919). The donation came (presumably) in two sections: one in 1989, and another some time following. They were transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2000.
Search Terms
Churchill, Ruth Pierson, 1896-; Château-Thierry (France)--Description and travel--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--War work--France--Personal narratives, American
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material may also be found in the Smith College Archives Class of 1919 files (under Pierson, Ruth Vail), and the Class of 1950 files (under Churchill, Martha Ann, Ruth's daughter). There is also related information in the Smith College Archives War Service files, including records of the Smith College Relief Unit and the Smith College Canteen Unit (under the YMCA).
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Outline of Methodist War Relief Service, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - News clippings, 1919-88 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing
    - Family, 1919-20 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Incoming
    - Brother-in-law, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Malcolm Campbell, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Henry Draeger, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rev. Albert Hall Marion, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Andre Chevalier, 1920-21, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Maurice Chevalier, 1920-21, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Leone Provost Faure, 1920-65, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Madame Frederick, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - L. Gabiot, 1921-29, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Veuve Harle, 1920-29, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Jeannine Issartel, 1946-49, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Simone Plateau, 1920-29, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Marie Salmon, 1921-22, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Julian S. Wadsworth, 1919-29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA
  - Photographs/Postcards, ca.1919 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1919 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bankbook, 1919-20 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Christmas Card List?, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Michelin and Cie, eds., La Deuxieme Bataille de la Marne, 1914-1918, (Clairmont-Ferrand, France: Michelin, 1919) (Box 1, Folder 26)